<?xml version='1.0'?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
]>

<chapter id="The_Open_Source_Way-Communities_of_Practice">
  <title>Communities of practice</title>
  <section id="The_Open_Source_Way-Communities_of_Practice-Introduction">
    <title>Introduction</title>
    <blockquote><attribution>Tom Peters, about Etienne Wenger's book <citetitle>Communities of Practice</citetitle></attribution>
    <para>
      The idea that an organization is a constellation of "communities
      of practice" is a genuine breakthrough, and that overused word
      "breakthrough" is merited.  It is an idea that had profound
      implications for what it takes to run a successful organization
      in our frenetic, chaotic times.  In this book, Wenger lays the
      groundwork for the kind of thinking that will be necessary for
      any surviving organization in the 21st century.  Wenger and the
      Institute for Research on Learning are defining the cutting
      edge.  And they are right!  Pay attention!  Please!''
    </para>
    </blockquote>
  </section>
  <section id="The_Open_Source_Way-Communities_of_Practice-What_is_a_Community_of_Practice">
    <title>What is a Community of Practice?</title>
    <para>
      It seems to be a commonly held opinion that principles of the
      open source way are limited to the practice of software
      development.
    </para>
    <para>
      In fact, the open source way is an instance of a ''community of
      practice'', which exist in varying forms all around us.  Etienne
      Wenger, the leading theorist of communities of practice,
      [http://www.ewenger.com/theory/ defines] the term as follows:
    </para>
    <blockquote><attribution>Etienne Wenger</attribution>
    <para>
      Communities of practice are formed by people who engage in a
      process of collective learning in a shared domain of human
      endeavor: a tribe learning to survive, a band of artists seeking
      new forms of expression, a group of engineers working on similar
      problems, a clique of pupils defining their identity in the
      school, a network of surgeons exploring novel techniques, a
      gathering of first-time managers helping each other cope. In a
      nutshell: <emphasis role="bold">Communities of practice are
      groups of people who share a concern or a passion for something
      they do and learn how to do it better as they interact
      regularly.</emphasis>
    </para>
    </blockquote>
  </section>
  <section id="The_Open_Source_Way-Communities_of_Practice-Elements_of_the_Community_of_Practice">
    <title>Elements of the Community of Practice</title>
    <para>
      Every community of practice consists of three structural
      elements:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para><firstterm>Domain</firstterm>.  The domain is
      the area of knowledge that interests the community.  In free
      software, the domain is usually a particular technical problem
      that needs to be solved.</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para><firstterm>Community.</firstterm> The community
      is the set of people who care enough about the domain to give
      their own time to participate.  In free software, even though
      domain may be very specific, interested community members can
      come from anywhere that's connected to the Internet -- which is
      one of the factors that makes the community software development
      model so powerful.</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para><firstterm>Practice.</firstterm> The practice is
      the way that work is done, by the community, to further their
      goals in regard to the domain.  All frameworks, tools, ideas,
      stories, documents, legal entities, code, and so forth, are all
      part of the practice.  It's the work, and all the tools used to
      get the work done.</para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
  <section id="The_Open_Source_Way-Communities_of_Practice-Principles_for_Cultivating_Communities_of_Practice">
    <title>Principles for Cultivating Communities of Practice</title>
    <para>
      In his book <citetitle>Cultivating Communities of
      Practice</citetitle>, Etienne Wenger proposes seven principles
      for successfully cultivating communities of practice.  Anyone
      who is responsible for moving a community forward towards its
      goals should consider reading it.
    </para>
   <section id="The_Open_Source_Way-Communities_of_Practice-Design_for_evolution">
     <title>Design for evolution</title>
     <!-- Principle -->
     <para>
       When starting a new community effort, it's difficult to know
       what form it will take.  Volunteers are not employees; they can
       only be influenced, never ordered.  Some may take passionately
       to the proposed project; others may only be able to give some
       of their time.
     </para>
     <!-- Implementation -->
     <para>
       Be ready for that.  Concentrate on simple lists that encourage
       accountability.  Know who's doing what.  Maintain a flexibility
       of structure, so that if someone to have an idea that takes
       your effort in a completely different direction, you don't have
       to change all your rules.  Only have as much "governance" as
       you need at the time, never more.
     </para>
     <para>
       Also: volunteers leave.  It's a fact of life.  Make it easy to
       hand off tasks to newcomers, and work to generate newcomers, so
       that your old-timers don't feel obliged to continue doing work
       that they no longer have the time or inclination to do.
     </para>
     <!-- Example -->
     <para>
       At <ulink
       url="http://teachingopensource.org">teachingopensource.org</ulink>,
       there are a number of working groups.  Some of them are active;
       some of them are not.  Creating a new working group is
       deliberately kept simple; identify a "leader" in charge of
       moving things forward, and claim a wiki page, and you're all
       set.  Working groups are evaluated periodically by the entire
       group, and if it's generally agreed that no progress is being
       made -- often because the leader doesn't have the time required
       -- the working group either finds a new leader, or is
       disbanded.  Simple process, until more complex process is
       needed.
     </para>
   </section>
   <section id="The_Open_Source_Way-Communities_of_Practice-Open_a_dialogue_between_inside_and_outside_perspectives">
      <title>Open a dialogue between inside and outside perspectives</title>
      <!-- Principle -->
      <para>
	In any community there are always "insiders" -- i.e., the
	people who understand the problem space very well, the people
	who are at the core of the domain space -- and people who are
	"outsiders", but have enthusiasm, some domain knowledge, and a
	willingness to help.  A successful community uses both of
	these perspectives effectively, because it's the outsiders who
	are most likely to impart new energy and new perspectives.
      </para>
      <!-- Implementation -->
      <para>
	There are different kinds of insiders and outsiders.  A
	company's employees can be the insiders, and the customers can
	be the outsiders.  One particular team can be the insiders,
	and other employees can be the outsiders.  Beyond companies,
	longtime members of a community become insiders over time, and
	newcomers almost always start as outsiders.
      </para>
      <!-- Example -->
      <para>
	For example, when Red Hat first started the Fedora project,
	many of the critical decisions were taken by a committee
	composed only of Red Hat engineers.  A number of critical
	tasks were assigned to "insiders", and these tasks languished.
	In the meantime the "outsiders" struggled to find meaningful
	tasks to help the project's growth.  The public perception
	looked a lot like <ulink
	url="http://lwn.net/Articles/83360/">this</ulink>.  The
	dialogue between the groups made it clear that externalizing
	the tools and processes were key to community growth.
      </para>
   </section>
   <section id="The_Open_Source_Way-Communities_of_Practice-Invite_different_levels_of_participation">
     <title>Invite different levels of participation</title>
     <!-- Principle -->
     <para>
       Often, the hard tasks at the center of a domain can only be
       tackled by the insiders -- but if only the hardest tasks get
       focus, and only by experts, then those new to the domain do not
       have opportunities to gain expertise.
     </para>
     <!-- Implementation -->
     <para>
       One of the important concepts espoused by Wenger is
       <firstterm>legitimate peripheral participation</firstterm>.  It
       is, essentially, the idea of apprenticeship; the key difference
       is that, rather than being apprenticed to an individual, a new
       practitioner can be apprenticed to the entire community of
       practice.
     </para>
     <para>
       In a volunteer community especially, people who join are going
       to be invested in learning more and doing more, and it's
       important to identify work that matches the newbie's skills,
       invites them to stretch those skills, and provides people who
       can help them develop those skills as required.
     </para>
     <!-- Example -->
     <para>
       As an example, learning to package software is not easy -- but
       some software is easier to package than others.  Newbie Fedora
       packagers are invited to learn how to package fonts, since they
       are simple and very uniform in how they are packaged.  There
       are also lots and lots of fonts out there that need to be
       packaged.  It's a perfect "on-ramp" for newbie packagers, and
       because there are so many fonts to be packaged, there are
       plenty of opportunities for newbies to be immediately useful.
     </para>
     <important>
       <title>Experts are great, but they're hard to find.</title>
       <para>
	 Experts are great, but they're hard to find.  The way to find
	 more experts is to invest in a process that continually
	 creates more experts.
       </para>
     </important>
   </section>
   <section id="The_Open_Source_Way-Communities_of_Practice-Develop_both_public_and_private_community_spaces">
     <title>Develop both public and private community spaces</title>
     <!-- Principle -->
     <para>
       Avoiding the cabal mentality does <emphasis
       role="bold">not</emphasis> mean having every single
       conversation in public, ever.  Transparency is great, but it is
       unreasonable to expect everyone to be comfortable with full
       transparency, all the time.
     </para>
     <!-- Implementation -->
     <para>
       Also, one-to-one communication builds intimacy and trust that
       multiway communication cannot.  Especially as new participants
       are building confidence, it's vitally important to build
       private relationships between individuals.  Certainly it is
       appropriate to encourage important conversations to be moved
       into public forums, especially conversations about actions that
       will affect others.  But private chats are important too, and
       often useful for eliciting insights that help move the more
       public conversations forward.
     </para>
     <!-- Example -->
     <para>
       In particular, private conversations can be critical to
       resolving conflicts within communities, and community leaders
       who are seen as responsible for the community's health should
       be comfortable taking the parties aside.  There have been many
       examples in the Fedora community of conflicts that were better
       resolved in private, and there will be more in the future.
     </para>
   </section>
   <section id="The_Open_Source_Way-Communities_of_Practice-Focus_on_value">
     <title>Focus on value</title>
     <!-- Principle -->
     <para>
       No volunteer wants to spend time on work that nobody values.
       Therefore, encourage community members to express the value
       that they receive from the community, and to reflect on the
       value that they provide.
     </para>
     <!-- Implementation -->
     <para>
       Also understand that not everyone's notion of value needs to
       agree; so long as participants do not actually detract by
       participating, they should feel free to add value in whatever
       way they see fit.  Core participants frequently do not value a
       set of contributions initially, and only come to understand and
       appreciate that value later.  Even contributions that are
       wildly experimental and far from the mainstream, and may not
       seem at all valuable, should be respected and encouraged.
     </para>
     <!-- Example -->
     <para>
       Example: There was a time, not so long ago, when many central
       members of the Fedora community saw a Live CD as a waste of
       effort.  The Live CD is now one the most important deliverables
       of the entire Fedora community.  But it was clear to the
       initial contributors that a good Live CD was critically
       valuable, and the community's embrace of that work led to a
       critical mass of contributors to focus on, and solve, the
       problem.
     </para>
   </section>
   <section id="The_Open_Source_Way-Communities_of_Practice-Combine_familiarity_and_excitement">
     <title>Combine familiarity and excitement</title>
     <!-- Principle -->
     <para>
       Stable and familiar working processes are vital, because people
       need tasks to focus their day-to-day work.
     </para>
     <!-- Implementation -->
     <para>
       Still, people can not thrive on heads-down tasks alone.
       Exciting new challenges create opportunities to energize old
       friends and attract new ones, and give volunteers an important
       sense that they are all wrapped up in a great and important
       challenge.  This excitement is crucially important to keep
       volunteers motivated on the daily work.
     </para>
     <!-- Example -->
     <para>
       <replaceable>Example needed.</replaceable>
     </para>
   </section>
   <section id="The_Open_Source_Way-Communities_of_Practice-Create_a_rhythm_for_the_community">
     <title>Create a rhythm for the community</title>
     <!-- Principle -->
     <para>
       The pace of engagement is crucially important in a community of
       doers.
     </para>
     <!-- Implementation -->
     <para>
       Moving too quickly and demanding too much, too soon, can leave
       volunteers frantic and feeling like they can't keep up.  Moving
       too slowly can lose volunteers who do not see enough activity
       to hold their own interest.
     </para>
     <!-- Example -->
     <para>
       The weekly IRC meeting has been a hallmark of most successful
       Fedora projects.  For some projects, a weekly meeting may be
       too much, and for other projects, a weekly meeting may only be
       a way to checkpoint activity that is going on constantly.
       Either way, building and maintaining a sense of rhythm is
       crucial for a healthy community.
     </para>
   </section>
 </section>
 <section id="The_Open_Source_Way-Communities_of_Practice-Learn_more">
   <title>Learn more</title>
   <para>
     To learn more about how to cultivate communities of practice,
     read Etienne Wenger's book on the subject:
   </para>
   <para>
     <ulink url="http://www.amazon.com/Cultivating-Communities-Practice-Etienne-Wenger/dp/1578513308"/>
   </para>
 </section>
</chapter>
